Recording my phone?
We're recording.
Okay, just... alright.
בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
We're in מסכת זבחים Masechet Zevachim
דף ד Daf Daled right at the top of the דף daf
and we're going to unpack something that's going to get a little
complicated, but hopefully if we keep a bird's eye view we'll be
able to see what we're doing. Hold on.
I really see today a little bit more of I don't know
learning together because I was drowning in זבחים. Zevachim. Okay, this is
what I'm understanding.
At the first משנה Mishnah of this מסכת, masechet, if you want
to look back, it says כל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא לשמן כשרים אלא
שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה.
Kol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishmam kshairim ela
shelo alu labaalim leshem hovah. All the sacrifices, this is the very
first lines of the first משנה mishnah of this מסכת. masechet. All
the sacrifices that were slaughtered not for their sake,
they're kosher, they can I guess be eaten or used, but they
don't fulfill whatever obligation the owner of this sacrifice set out
to do. So now, בוקר טוב, boker tov, so now we're going
to unpack each one of the עבודות הדם, avodot hadam, the blood
works of the sacrifice. Standard procedure. Blood work. Well
I don't know how to say it, עבודות הדם. avodot hadam.
That's good.
Service of the blood. To see that each one of them separately
also has proof how it must be done לשמה. lishma. And we're
going to look at it from two perspectives. One is the קודש
kodesh of the sacrifice, i.e., if I set out to bring a
קרבן שלמים korban shelamim it must be a שלמים shelamim in my
mind and not become whatever an עולה olah or a חטאת chatat
or something else. And so one aspect is from the קודש kodesh
of the קרבן korban and the other aspect is from the owner.
I if I have to bring it, I have to bring it
then I can't be like oh you bring it for me or
I'll use your קרבן korban already for what I have in mind.
Okay? So we have one is the קודש kodesh of the
קרבן, korban, you're welcome to chime in, and one is the בעלי
הקרבן. ba'alei hakorban. Hopefully that's okay. And we have four עבודות
הדם.
avodot
hadam. Everybody knows it.
We learned it last time. Huh? We learned this last cycle.
Last cycle? I was still in preschool so I wasn't here.
Okay, we have שחיטה, shechitah, קבלה, kabbalah,
זריקה, zrikah, and הולכה holachah or backwards order. And so what we're
going to have to do is go through each one of them
and prove from the text where we can see that each one
of them has text proof that it must be לשמה lishma for
its sake. Okay. This is our task this morning. We're going to
do it for the קודש kodesh and for the owner and it
we might get a little bit lost so we'll try to refer
back to the bird's view and see where we're going with it.
So the first of the עבודות avodot can be done by the
owner.
Huh?
The owner can שחט shecht
the offer.
The owner has to do it. We'll see that this is the
main, the זריקה zrikah is the main thing the owner is obligated
for, but let's just go by order because it's already...
The כהן kohen does the זריקה. zrikah. Huh? The כהן kohen does
the זריקה zrikah but the שחיטה, shechitah, yeah, the שחיטה. shechting.
The שחיטה, shechting, yeah.
The כוונה kavvanah or the לשמה lishma piece.
Oh no no, he's just saying who can do it.
Yeah, okay.
I think you two were talking in different things. Yeah. Keep going.
Okay, at the top of דף ד. Daf Daled.
מנלן דבעינן זביחה לשמה? Menalan d'ba'inan zvicha lishma? How do we know
this? Where is our prooftext that we have to do זביחה, zvicha,
that we have to do the slaughtering for its own sake? We
have a פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra ג, א, Gimmel Aleph, ואם
זבח שלמים קרבנו. ve'im zevach shelamim korbano. So it's like a little
bit, we don't need one of those words. We could say ואם
שלמים קרבנו ve'im shelamim korbano or ואם זבח קרבנו. ve'im zevach korbano.
Why do we have...
you haven't set it up, I know.
Good.
We don't want to be on... this morning and I
remember... okay,
we're still at the top of... we're still at the top of...
So מנלן דבעינא זביחה לשמה? Menalan d'beinan zvicha lishmah? דאמר קרא ואם
זבח שלמים קורבנו, D'amar kra ve'im zevach shelamim korbano, שתהא זביחה לשם
השלמים. shetehei zvicha leshem hashelamim. So we understand from the extra word
זבח שלמים zevach shelamim that the slaughtering, the זבח zevach needs to
be for the sake of the שלמים. shelamim. ודילמא היינו שמיה? Vedilma
hainu shmeih? Maybe it's simply its name, just like I have a
קורבן עולה korban olah or חטאת chatat or something like this, this
קורבן, korban, its name is זבח שלמים. zevach shelamim.
So then we have other פסוקים psukim that show me otherwise. מדכתיב
המקריב את דם השלמים, Midechtiv hamakriv et dam hashelamim, הזורק את דם
השלמים, hazorek et dam hashelamim, ולא כתיב זבח. v'lo ktiv zevach. Like
in other places we say, the one who sacrifices, or we'll see,
brings near the blood of the שלמים. shelamim. So therefore the זבח
השלמים zevach hashelamim cannot be
its
name, right? Because otherwise it would have said המקריב את דם זבח
השלמים, hamakriv et dam zevach hashelamim, right, if that was the name.
So therefore we understand from this that it's not its name. ולא
כתיב זבח. V'lo ktiv zevach. ובהא כתיב זבח. Ubeha ktiv zevach. And
in the first פסוק pasuk it does say זבח. zevach. שמע מינה
שתהא זביחה לשם שלמים. Shma mina shetehei zvicha leshem shelamim. From there
we understand that our first of the four עבודות, avodot, the זביחה
zvicha has to be for the sake of שלמים. shelamim. Yes sir.
This only applies strictly speaking to שלמים. shelamim. Okay. There are lots
of other types of קורבנות. korbanot.
That way, now let's do it here.
I didn't prepare the דף. daf.
If you but if that's but if
that'd be קודשי קודשים kodshei kodashim then קל וחומר kal vachomer קודשי.
kodshei.
I didn't sleep all night long. Huh?
All questions for tomorrow. Okay. אשכחן זביחה שאר עבודות מנלן? Ashkchan zvicha
shear avodot menalan? So this little פסוק pasuk exercise that we just
did helps us find why זביחה zvicha has to be לשמה, lishmah,
but what about the three other עבודות avodot that are left?
וכי תימא ליליף מזביחה? Vechi teima leilyif mizevicha? So can we learn
it from זביחה? zvicha? Can we say the same way that the
slaughtering has to be לשמה, lishmah, so let's say the same about
everything else? Now we'll see that each one of these עבודות, avodot,
they're like a Venn diagram if I understand it correctly,
they overlap in some things and they
don't
overlap in others.
It'll get started in a minute, just keep on going.
Okay, so
they
have some things in common with each other and some things that
they don't. So the זביחה... zvicha... you can talk if you want.
Don't
worry, don't worry, ignore it. Okay, there we go.
Okay, so what is one of the things that is different from
the זביחה zvicha to the three other
עבודות? avodot? Welcome to those joining us now, apologies for the delay.
We're in זבחים, Zevachim, top of דף ד' עמוד א'. daf daled
amud alef. We're looking at the ד' עבודות הדם. arba avodot hadam.
We just showed that the זבח zevach has to be לשמה lishmah
and now we're looking at the others. Okay, so about the זביחה
zvicha it says שכן נפסלה שלא לשם אוכליו בפסח. sheken nifsela shelo
leshem ochlav bepesach. In the זביחה, zvicha, in the slaughtering, we have
a special חומרא chumra regarding פסח. Pesach. The פסח Pesach offering is
disqualified
if it's slaughtered not for the sake of those that eat it.
If a person, for example, who's going to slaughter it is too
sick or feeble for some reason can't eat enough of the right
amount, then they can't do it. So we can't learn from this
to the others. So let's find another פסוק. pasuk. אלא
אמר קרא המקריב
את דם השלמים שתהא קבלה לשם שלמים.
Ela amar kra hamakriv et dam hashelamim
shetehei kabbalah leshem shelamim.
We have a different פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra 7:33
that says the one that המקריב hamakriv
the blood of peace offering, and המקריב hamakriv we kind of on
one hand it sacrifices but it also is to bring close, right,
from קרוב. karov. So it's like the one that gathers. In this
פסוק pasuk indicates שתהא קבלה לשם שלמים shetehei kabbalah leshem shelamim
because it says המקריב את דם השלמים hamakriv et dam hashelamim indicates
that collecting the blood also must be performed for the sake of
the שלמים. shelamim.
I'm sorry, what else could it have said?
It could have said
maybe something like... anything else instead of מקריב makriv like there's some
understanding about this verb that indicates קבלה kabbalah indicates collecting of collecting
the blood
that the קבלה kabbalah has to be for the sake of שלמים.
shelamim.
Not sure what else. Tell me what what's the question?
Well what he's saying I don't see anything else. It could have
just said מקריב דמו makriv damo since it repeated שלמים shelamim again
then it
indicates it has
to be for the same שלמים.
shelamim. Yeah. This is what's going to happen with all the פסוקים.
pesukim. It's going to be very okay. Okay. ולכתוב
רחמנא בקבלה ונילף
שחיטה
מינה.
velichtov rachmana bakkabbalah veneilef
shechita
minnah.
Can I show you something? I tried to highlight it so I
can see the pattern so you'll see that the pattern keeps being
this. You want it now? I'll show you what I did with
my גמרא Gemara if it's legal.
See the colors? It's just going to woo yeah it's just going
to repeat and be a pattern that says אשכחן. ashkachan. Oh so
I found this. So can I learn from it the next one?
No I can't. I have a פסוק. pasuk. This is going to
be how the flow of the דף daf more or less. And
just when we think we got it it's going to change.
So okay.
Back to ולכתוב רחמנא בקבלה. velichtov rachmana bakkabbalah. So maybe we should
learn backwards right? ולכתוב רחמנא בקבלה ונילף שחיטה מינה. velichtov rachmana bakkabbalah
veneilef shechita minnah. Maybe we should derive the שחיטה shechita from
the קבלה kabbalah from collecting of
collecting the blood
that the קבלה kabbalah has to be for the sake of שלמים.
shelamim. Why? Because if קבלה kabbalah is שלמים shelamim שחיטה? shechita? Like
how do we know which direction the traffic is flowing right? How
do we know that we learn from the קרבן korban to the
collection as opposed to from the collection to the קרבן? korban? If
you ask too many questions you get to switch places with me
here. This is not my strength
so.
Meaning because we use the same process to learn this?
Yeah I'm trying to understand like what the logic is. Why would
you think one applies to the other? I mean you've brought two
separate שלמים.
shelamim. This is what they say. I think when I listen there's
places that also תוספות Tosafot is asking some of the same things
of like why are we learning it this way why are we
learning from one to the other why not from two to two?
I don't know what to tell you. This is what this is
where we are.
Okay so it could be the opposite but it's not. But here
we have so wait let's continue. Let's see if the גמרא Gemara
answers it and our own questions okay?
I think if you learn something about שלמים shelamim based on the
פסוק pasuk about זבחים zevachim right? And then we're applying that to
the קבלה kabbalah because of the word קרוב karov right? So but
it's like why couldn't we learn the thing about שלמים shelamim in
the פסוק pasuk about קבלה kabbalah and then apply it to שלמים
shelamim since שלמים shelamim is in both פסוקים pesukim why are we
learning one direction and not the other direction?
Right. But the גמרא Gemara is going to answer. So just like
let's hang. I read something nice over the weekend about somebody who
was teaching יבמות Yevamot and after he taught it forty times he
said I think I'm finally beginning to understand what's going on here.
So I feel very humbled by the גמרא Gemara in general and
this מסכת masechet specifically.
We'll do the best we can and then we can come back
to it and come back to it etc. Okay. So we have
a like a refutation right? משום דאיכא למיפרך מה לקבלה שכן פסולה
בזר ואשה. mishum deika lemeifrach mah lakkabbalah sheken pesulah bezar veishah.
So we can't learn them from each other because
there
is something that is and this is what I said earlier that
it's like a Venn diagram. They share things with each other but
they don't share everything with each other. And קבלה kabbalah my understanding
קבלה kabbalah has a special חומרא. chumra. The שחיטה shechita I don't
know if it helps us to write this had a חומרא chumra
of פסח Pesach right? The person that is going to eat the
פסח Pesach must be the one that prepares it. The קבלה kabbalah
is that
it must be with a כהן. Kohen. The כהן Kohen must do
the קבלה. kabbalah.
A male כהן.
Kohen.
I mean
yeah but
just is
it possible
a female כהן Kohen a כהנת? Kohenet?
Let's see if this works. Okay so a male כהן. Kohen.
You're right. A שחיטה, Shechitah, a woman can do a שחיטה. Shechitah.
A זר Zar can do a שחיטה Shechitah too, but the קבלה
Kabbalah has to be done by a כהן. Kohen. Okay?
This is what we just said. So therefore we cannot assume that
the הלכה Halachah that applies to the collection applies to the slaughter
as well. Good? Okay. אשכחן שחיטה וקבלה. Ashkachan shechitah vekabbalah. So I
found the שחיטה, Shechitah, זביחה, Zvichah, and קבלה. Kabbalah. זריקה מנלן? Zrikah
menalan? How do I know that the זריקה, Zrikah, the sprinkling of
the blood, has to be לשמה? Lishma? So now we're going to
see it, how we could learn it and how we don't learn
it, and then how we do learn it. Okay. וכי תימא נילף
מהני. Vechitayma neleaf mehanni. מה הני שכן טעונות צפון וישנן בחטאות הפנימיות.
Mah hanni sheken te'unot tzafon
veyeshnan bechata'ot hapnimiyot.
So again, we're looking at special חומרות Chumrot that apply to
one of the עבודות Avodot that don't apply to the other. So
we could derive from the
זביחה Zvichah and קבלה, Kabbalah, from the slaughter and from the collection.
What is unique about them, right? That there's a special location where
they need to be done. קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim need to be
done לצפון Latzafon and לשמה, Lishma, and the
other
עבודות Avodot are different in that sense.
The זריקה Zrikah can be done on all portions of the temple
courtyard.
Okay. אלא אמר קרא. Ella amar kra. So now we have a
different פסוק. Pasuk. הזורק את דם השלמים שתהא זריקה לשם שלמים. Hazorek
et dam hashlamim shetehay zrikah leshem shelamim.
In ויקרא Vayikra 7:14, in Leviticus 7:14, we have a פסוק Pasuk
that says הזורק את דם השלמים, Hazorek et dam hashlamim, who sprinkles
the blood of the peace offering. So that indicates to us that
the sprinkling of the blood has to be performed for the sake
of דם השלמים. Dam hashlamim. Okay. ולכתוב רחמנא בזריקה
ונילף
מינה. Velichtov Rachmana bezrikah ve-neleaf minah. So challenge: let רחמנא Rachmana write
this הלכה Halachah only with regards to the זריקה, Zrikah, and we
would learn from it that it applies to the שחיטה Shechitah and
the קבלה. Kabbalah. So how about if we go backwards? Can't go
backwards משום דאיכא למיפרך. Mishum de-ika lemeifach.
So same same flow. מה לזריקה שכן חייב עליה זר מיתה? Mah
lezrikah sheken chayav aleha zar mitah? The special stringency, special
חומרה Chumrah with the זריקה. Zrikah. What's special about it? That somebody
who is not a כהן, Kohen, who is a זר, Zar, will
be punished with death, or כרת Karet I think it should be,
for performing it. Okay.
אשכחן כולהו הולכה
מנלן.
Ashkacha kulhu
holachah menalan. So we have
the
three עבודות, Avodot, we explain how they're same and how they're not,
and now we're going to the
הולכה. Holachah. אשכחן כולהו הולכה מנלן? Ashkacha kulhu holachah menalan?
How do we know that this also supposed to be done לשמה?
Lishma? וכי תימא נילף מכולהו. Vechitayma neleaf mikulhu. Same structure.
מה לכולהו שכן עבודה שאי אפשר לבטלה תאמר בהולכה שאפשר לבטלה? Mah
lekulhu sheken avodah she-i efshar levatlah tomar beholachah she-efshar levatlah? What if
we say,
okay hold on a second...
so if all the other, right, all the other עבודות Avodot have
to be performed for the sake of the קרבן, Korban, right, לשמה,
Lishma, then this can be said.
What's unique about all these other ones? מה לכולהו שכן עבודה שאי
אפשר לבטלה תאמר בהולכה שאפשר לבטלה?
Mah lekulhu sheken avodah
she-i efshar levatlah tomar beholachah she-efshar levatlah? They are unique that each
one of them is we saw is indispensable עבודה. Avodah. Would we
say that any requirements any requirement that applies to those rights necessarily
applies also with regards to the הולכה, Holachah, to taking the blood,
which could be dispensable?
Hold on a second. Like if
the if the שחיטה Shechitah is done on the side of the
altar or like on a different place, then we would not have
to do the הולכה, Holachah, right? We would not have to carry
it. We don't have anywhere to carry it because we already we
are where we're supposed to be, right? אלא אמר קרא. Ella amar
kra. We have a פסוק Pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra first chapter. והקריב.
Vehikriv. the whole, המזבחה. hamizbecha.
We've sacrificed the whole thing, right? So this is the עולה ola
upon on the altar, on the מזבח. mizbeach.
ואמר מר, ve'amar mar, זו הולכת איברים לכבש. zu holachat evarim lakevesh.
So this is the carrying the limbs, right? Carrying the
parts
of the offerings to the כבש, kevesh, to the ramp that goes
up to the altar. ותניא, vetanya, same same place, והקריבו. vehikrivu.
So there's some act of bringing close. The הולכה holacha is derived
from this להקריב lehakriv because להקריב lehakriv means to sacrifice, but also
we know in Hebrew קרוב karov is to be close, to be
a relative. So that means that there is a specific verb and
therefore the הולכה holacha has to be לשמה. lishma.
זו קבלת הדם. zu kabbalat hadam. ואפיק רחמנא בלשון הולכה למימרא דהולכה
לא תפקה מכלל קבלה. ve'afik rachmana bilshon holacha lemeimra deholacha lo tafka
miklal kabala. And we can infer that God, that רחמנא
rachmana expresses the collection of the blood in the same way that
it's
used
for the קבלה kabala to say that
we
should not exclude the הולכה, holacha, sorry, הולכה holacha from the קבלה,
kabala, right? That they're connected together. No? Are we
kind
of kind of okay? Okay. So far so good. Okay, so this
is a location, right? Can we say this is about the that
the location still means we have to bring the blood? Yes. I'm
a little hesitant here, but okay. So we explain why each one
of them needs a different פסוק, pasuk, in what way each one
of them is not the same as the other. Each one of
them has a different פסוק pasuk that says this must be done
לשמה. lishma. So now we have all these four. But now we
have also another way that there could be a שינוי shinui in
the קרבן, korban, which is the which will change the לשמה, lishma,
the purposefulness on it. And again we understand from the משנה mishna
that the קרבן korban itself is going to be כשר, kasher, but
it's not going to fulfill what the person set out to do.
Okay. So the next piece is, if we completed these four, ואשכחן
שינוי קודש שינוי בעלים מנלן. ve'ashkechan shinui kodesh shinui be'alim minalan.
From where do we derive the הלכות
halachot regarding the owner? That
it
can't be slaughtered for somebody who is not the owner?
Okay. אמר רב פנחס בריה דרב אמי אמר קרא amar Rav Pinchas
brei deRav Ami amar kra in ויקרא Vayikra chapter seven, ובשר זבח
תודת שלמיו uvasar zevach todah shelamav שתהא זביחה לשם תודה shetehei zvicha
leshem todah ואי אינו עניין לשינוי קודש דנפקא לן מהתם תנהו עניין
לשינוי בעלים.
ve'i eino inyan leshinui kodesh de'nafka lan mehatam tnehu inyan leshinui
be'alim. Okay.
So that the פסוק pasuk says the meat of the sacrifice of
the תודה, todah, of the thanksgiving peace offering will be eaten on
the day of this offering. I,
being in a family with many vegans and vegetarians, this was a
lot of,
you know, whatever, things going through my mind. I'm married to a
vegan. But the תודה todah sacrifice especially to be eaten on that
day, clearly when the person slaughters, he's going to slaughter too much
meat for himself, we hope, that something that is a portion that
he can't eat, he'll have to invite other people. And when he
invites other people, they'll be like, oh, what are we celebrating? And
then he'll have to tell what he's thankful for and, you know,
whatever, advertise or, right, promote the שם השם. shem Hashem. So that
the זביחה zvicha in that sense should be for the sake of
the of the תודה. todah. שתהא זביחה לשם תודה. shetehei zvicha leshem
todah.
It's also interesting, another conversation that we're heading into is how much
meat people ate back then with this system as opposed to how
much meat generally in our society we eat today. There's a chance
that if we had to bring an offering and watch the animal
and give up an animal and all that, that this is an
activity that happened less often than going to the store and buying
some pink thing that's already breaded and I just have to put
in the oven.
Like, also most of these are small animals.
You mean
sheep. Sheep and goats. Now.
Yeah,
okay, so even more. Okay. Okay. Let's go back.
Okay, so if, so the גמרא Gemara says: אם
אינו
עניין לשינוי קודש, דנפקא
לן מהתם, תנהו עניין לשינוי בעלים.
Im eino inyan lishinui kodesh, dinafka lan me-hatam, tnahu inyan
lishinui be'alim. If
this is superfluous, if we don't need this language for שינוי קודש
shinui kodesh because we already proved these four things from other פסוקים,
pesukim, let's use it for talking about a שינוי shinui in the
בעלים. be'alim. Let's apply it to when there is a change in
regards to the owner of the קרבן. korban. והאי להכי הוא דאתא?
Ve-hai lehachi hu de-ata? Is that, is that what it comes to
teach? Does it come to teach this הלכה? halacha? המיבעי ליה לכדתניא:
ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו. Ha mibai lei le-chidetanya: u-vesar zevach todat shelamav.
We're repeating this פסוק, pasuk,
because we have a teaching in the ברייתא beraita for this פסוק:
pasuk: ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו. u-vesar zevach todat shelamav. אבא חנין אומר
משום רבי אליעזר: בא ללמד תודה ששחטה לשם שלמים, כשרה. שלמים ששחטן
לשם תודה, פסולה.
Abba Chanin omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer: ba le-lammed todah she-shechatah le-shem shelamim,
kesherah. Shelamim she-shechatan
le-shem todah, pesulah.
Let me finish and then we'll go back. מה הפרש בין זה
לזה? תודה קרויה שלמים ואין שלמים קרויים תודה.
Mah hefresh bein zeh le-zeh? Todah keruyah shelamim ve-ein
shelamim keruyim todah. I'm thinking of it as all frogs are green,
not all green things are frogs. Okay? So it's like they we
sometimes use them sort of interchangeably, that green thing, but they're not
exactly interchangeable. So how are they different? The תודה ששחטה לשם שלמים
כשרה. todah she-shechatah le-shem shelamim kesherah. If we offer a thanks offering
for the sake of the שלמים, shelamim, right, of the peace offering,
that would be okay. But backwards, peace offering to do for the
sake of thanksgiving is not okay. It's going to make it פסול
pasul and it's not going to fulfill what the owner of the
sacrifice wanted to do. It's a one-way street between the שלמים shelamim
and the תודה. todah. Okay. Yes, kind of.
Okay. אנן מזבח קאמרינן. Anan mi-zevach ka'amrinan.
So we can, we can derive it from the term זבח, zevach,
right? Because we saw earlier that we can do without it. When
it says זבח השלמים,
zevach
ha-shelamim, it could have just said השלמים ha-shelamim without the word זבח.
zevach. And therefore,
the sacrifice, the זבח, zevach, it has to be performed for the
sake of the owner.
This is, this is what we learned from the אבא חנין. Abba
Chanin. Okay. ואכתי מיבעי ליה: חטאת ואשם מנין? תלמוד לומר: זבח.
Ve-achti mibai lei: chatat ve-asham minayin? Talmud
lomar: zevach. רגע, rega, just
pause.
The term זבח, zevach,
we still need it, right, to talk about another halakhic matter. When
we talk about the meat of the חטאת chatat and the אשם,
asham, the sin offering and the guilt offering,
that they also have to be, have to be eaten on the
day the animal is sacrificed and that following night like a thanks
offering. We can raise a question about it. Maybe it's the same,
the thanks and the and the חטאת chatat and the אשם. asham.
The verse states ובשר זבח שלמיו. u-vesar zevach shelamav. The meat of
the sacrifice of the שלמים shelamim shall be eaten on this day.
So not only thanks offering, but any other slaughter could be subject
to this time limit unless the תורה Torah tells us otherwise.
Okay.
If so, אם כן נכתוב קרא: ובשר תודת שלמיו זבח. im ken
nichtov kra: u-vesar todat shelamav zevach. מאי
זבח? שמע
מינה תרתי.
Mai zevach? Shema
mina tarti.
So if the term זבח, zevach, right,
indicates only that the חטאת chatat and the אשם asham may be
eaten only for that limited time like the תודה, todah, like the
thanks offering, then maybe the verse should say and the ובשר תודת
שלמיו, u-vesar todat shelamav, the meat of the שלמים, shelamim,
the meat of the תודה todah of the שלמים, shelamim, right, of
the thanks- Thanksgiving of the peace offering sacrifice. When we mention the
word זבח zevach in this פסוק, pasuk, what does it help us?
That we can make two conclusions, says the גמרא. Gemara. Not sure
if it's completely clear but we can make two conclusions, I guess
one for the תודה Todah and one for the שלמים. Shelamim.
Okay, this was about the owner. Okay,
that we can't change
we can't change who's the owner. אשכחן זביחה שאר עבודות מנלן. ashkechan
zevichah shear avodot menalan. So we found
a
halakhic source for the slaughter, where do we derive the other עבודות?
avodot? וכי תימא לילף מזביחה מה לזביחה שכן פוסל שלא לשמו אוכלים
ופסח. vechi teima leilef mizevichah mah lizevichah sheken posel shelo lishmo ochlim
uvapesach. So we already said this, we brought this earlier when we
talked about the קודש, kodesh, now we're talking about the בעלים, bealim,
and the פסח Pesach proves to us the בעלים. bealim.
We know that if
the
person has to slaughter the פסח Pesach offering, the person who's bringing
the sacrifice has to slaughter the פסח Pesach offering for the sake
of those that eat it. And if for some reason he can't
eat it, he's sick or whatever and he can't eat the right
amount from it, then the קרבן korban is going to be פסול.
pasul. For everybody. For everybody, yes.
That's a big deal.
He should be able to eat it, or let somebody else do
it, no?
Well, what I'm thinking of, let's say you slaughter קרבן פסח korban
Pesach on the afternoon of the fourteenth of ניסן. Nisan. Okay. And
one of the people who's registered for it, you slaughter it with
the intention of having it eaten by everybody who's registered for it,
and one of the people who's part of your group becomes טמא.
tamei. Okay. And can't eat it.
So that's going to mess it up for everybody.
Even if he's not the one bringing the sacrifice, only if he's
the one eating
it? That's what you're saying? Yeah.
Okay. I think this is תוספות, Tosafot, but I don't remember what
they conclude.
From at least what they bring here, I think it has to
be the owner of the sacrifice that has to be able to
eat it, and if he can't, then it disqualifies.
So he's able to eat it, the owner, the owner is able
to eat it when it's sacrificed, but he becomes טמא tamei later
on, let's say a dead שרץ sheretz falls on him.
Right before, right, he's at the פסח Pesach meal, a dead שרץ
sheretz falls on him and all of a sudden he's טמא tamei
and he can't eat it anymore. Okay.
So then what does everybody do? Does that disqualify?
I don't know, but tomorrow there's going to be somebody here that
can answer everything.
Say it again?
You want to see Rabbi who ate a Seder earlier so he
can answer your question?
But if the rule is everybody who's in the group has to
eat it and one of them is
טמא tamei and can't eat it, what does that do to everybody
else in the group? Oh, I think I just remembered the answer.
I think the answer is as long as all the עבודות avodot
have been done, then it's okay.
Right, it's that it has to be done with those people in
mind.
If he touches a corpse between the time it's slaughtered and the
time the blood is sprinkled, it might be a problem.
Okay, so I think, and I'm totally in left field, I think
we're talking about the לשמה lishmah aspect of him bringing the קרבן.
korban.
Yeah, we're not talking about eating.
We're not yet talking about the טמא tamei aspect. Okay, sorry. Maybe.
Okay, and again, we're just showing how זביחה zevichah and we'll see
same but not same as everything else. So the זביחה zevichah has
an issue from פסח. Pesach. Okay, רגע. rega. נאמרה זביחה בשינוי קודש
ונאמרה זביחה בשינוי בעלים. ne'emrah zevichah bishinnui kodesh vene'emrah zevichah bishinnui bealim.
Okay,
so now we have, we talk about the זביחה, zevichah, the slaughtering,
in regards to the type of offering, right, the קודש, kodesh, like
what is it supposed to be, what kind of sacrifice it is,
and in regards to the owner. מה זביחה אמורה בשינוי קודש לא
חילקת בין זביחה לשאר עבודות אף זביחה אמורה בשינוי בעלים לא תחלק
בהם בין זביחה לשאר עבודות. mah zevichah amurah bishinnui kodesh lo chilakta
bein zevichah lishar avodot af zevichah amurah bishinnui bealim lo techallek bahem
bein zevichah lishar avodot. So like we did already this whole exercise,
right, and we showed that the זביחה zevichah is the same as
the other עבודות. avodot. They all end up having their own proof
לשמה. lishmah. This is what we found when we looked at the
קודש, kodesh, at the intent of the sacrifice. Let's do the same
for the owner. We'll say the זביחה zevichah can't have a שינוי
בעלים, shinnui bealim, the slaughter, and in the קודש kodesh we saw
that it applies to everything, let's say that it applies to all
the other עבודות. avodot. איכא למפרך, ika lemafrach, we have a refutation.
Okay.
How is this different? Where's the where's the owner? We'll see that
there's four different things that it's that it's different. Let's see if
we can find them and unpack them.
Okay. מה לשינוי בקודש Mah l'shinui bakodesh שכן פסולה בגופה sheken psulah
begufah one, וישנו בארבע עבודות v'yeshno b'arba avodot two, וישנו לאחר מיתה
v'yeshno l'achar mitah and וישנו בציבור כביחיד. v'yeshno b'tzibbur k'veyachid. Okay, let's
see what those mean, maybe.
Okay,
so the first one, שכן פסולה בגופה, sheken psulah begufah, it says,
that this disqualifies, concerns the offering itself, something can happen to the
offering itself. And the second one is the ארבע עבודות. arba avodot.
It applies to the four these rites I guess
they're called for קרבנות korbanot worship. And the this is
what I said earlier, and again you're
welcome to chime in, the זריקה zerikah is the important thing that
the owner will have כוונה kavanah to do. So that that signifies
that. And then ישנו לאחר מיתה. yeshno l'achar mitah. So what is
the status of the קרבן korban that the owner said he's going
to do after the owner is dead? Are the heirs of the
owner obligated to bring the
קרבן? korban? In some cases they can't. In some cases they don't
have to, and some cases they do have to. I think if
there is a specific נדר neder then the obligation continues because it's
sort of like a debt.
In most cases he can't, I think that's because that has to
be the person.
So I think at the moment at least the difference between a
נדר neder and a נדבה. nedavah. A נדר neder would be like
an obligation. So it would be as if I owe something to
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Like if I owe something, whatever, I
have a debt to the government, right, and I and I die
חס וחלילה, chas v'chalilah, then my kids are going to be stuck
with the debt. If I am a נודר noder to give an
animal for the sake of something, and this is my נדר, neder,
that obligation stays. But if it's a נדבה nedavah then not. Does
that match what we're learning? Right.
Rather than just a נדר neder
because
that's so personal. Right. But I think what we were saying yesterday
we were saying that a נדר neder somehow was more obligational than
a
נדבה.
nedavah. Rabbi Disin said נדר neder was a personal obligation and נדבה
nedavah was a gift but not as a personal obligation. Yeah.
So I think נדבה nedavah is more איש אשר ידבנו לבו. ish
asher yidvenu libo.
It's like, oh I feel like giving.
So נדר neder is also optional in the sense that
you don't have to take a נדר. neder. Yes. But once you
took a נדר, neder, then I think you're obligated to it. And
then it goes into this whole thing of who can annul somebody
else's נדר. neder. But I think that a נדר neder is like
a it's like a debt.
You whatever.
A debt doesn't
I don't know, I don't know if somebody makes a pledge at
what level the pledge is.
I'm just imagining like the like the clearest example would be like
you you make a thing הקדש, hekdesh, right? So then when you
die that cow is still הקדש hekdesh and so your kids are
still going to have to bring it. Right. Yeah. That's not connected
to you at all. That's like the thing itself. And then a
נדר neder seems to be somewhere in the middle, like it's connected
to you as a person and there's no particular animal that you
set aside for it. But like there's an obligation.
So that's also a question that I think we should
explore
further maybe not not here right now that yes there is a
there is a question between like specificity, right, of like I am
going to bring this particular animal for this particular cause or thing
to blah blah blah and then it remains. Or if I say,
"Wow this was beautiful, I'm going to give a gift," but I
don't specify then it doesn't obligate whatever. Okay,
something, something.
No.
Okay. וישנו בציבור כביחיד. v'yeshno b'tzibbur k'veyachid. So the fourth way that
it's unique, the ownership of the sacrifice, is that the it applies
differently with regards to ציבור, tzibbur, communal things, as well as יחיד,
yachid, individual offerings, right. The applying
an
owner to the communal offering is kind of irrelevant. Yes.
But even for an individual קרבן korban it's not, it's a מחלוקת
mahloket over whether if I, if I look at my sheep and
say זו עולה, zo olah, זו עולה, zo olah,
is that still my sheep?
Oh, is it already now not yours? At what point did you
relinquish the ownership of the sheep? Okay. רגע. rege.
We're plotting along here. ואף על גב, ve'af al gav, assuming none
of us have sheep and anything that we have to worry about
it right away, we're more trying to understand how they thought about
it.
Okay. ואף על גב דתרתי לאו דווקא תרתי מיהא דווקא. ve'af al
gav d'tertei lav davka tertei miha davka. They're like, okay, although two
of them are maybe not so דווקא davka good refutations, two of
them are still precise distinctions. מאי שנא שינוי בעלים דלא הוה פסולה
בגופו? mai shna shinuy be'alim d'lo hve psule begufo? In the,
the two that are not precise, first, okay,
what's the difference about the owner?
Okay, first that it's the פסולו בגופו psulo begufo in the, the
offering itself. Something about the גוף בהמה guf behema is פסול. pasul.
מחשבה בעלמא. machshava be'alma.
Does it have to be a פסול psul in the גוף guf
or is it enough that it's a thought, right, that he changed
his mind about what this לשמה, lishma, what this offering is about?
שינוי קודש נמי מחשבה בעלמא הוא אלא כיון דאחשבה פסלה. shinuy kodesh
nami machshava be'alma hu ela kevan d'achshava psala. Okay,
so we change the purposefulness of the offering through our thought, right,
like we disqualify it once we intend it for something else, if
I, again, if I understand correctly. הכי נמי כיון דאחשבה פסלה. hachi
nami kevan d'achshava psala.
So once here's a different intent, then he disqualified, like he brings
it up and he says it's like, yeah, I'm going to bring
a שלמים, shelamim, oh, actually let's make it an עולה, olah, then
now it's disqualified. ולרב פנחס בריה דרב מרי דאמר יש שינוי בעלים
לאחר מיתה תרתי מיהא איכא למיפרך.
u'lerav pinchas bre d'raw mari de'amar yesh shinuy be'alim le'achar mita
tertei miha ika lemifrach. רק רגע. rak rega. Okay.
The second, second problem, right, about the שינוי shinuy after the death.
רב פנחס rav pinchas says,
okay, the disqualification, right, applies only after the owner's death and this
is what we've I think spent time talking.
Okay,
I can read you what I have but I'm not sure that
I'm completely getting it. תרתי מיהא איכא למיפרך. tertei miha ika lemifrach.
So these two, these are two remaining distinctions based on which the
comparison between a deviation from the type of offering and a deviation
with regard to the owner can be refuted. Okay, so the death,
what we talked about and the פסלו בגופו psalo begufo
if something happens to the animal. אלא אמר רב אשי אמר קרא
ונרצה לו לכפר עליו ולא על חבירו.
ela amar rav ashi amar kra venirtza
lo lekhaper alav velo al chavero.
So we have a פסוק, pasuk, simple, ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. venirtza
lo lekhaper alav.
That word לו lo is kind of not absolutely needed, right? It
should be accepted to atone for him. So why does it say
לו? lo? It could have just said should be accepted to atone
for him. That extra לו lo indicates ולא על חבירו. velo al
chavero. Different לו lo and לו lo and לו, lo, but that
it must be for him and not for another person. והאי
להכי הוא דאתא?
ve'hai
lehachi hu de'ata?
Does this verse really come to teach us this הלכה? halacha? הא
מיבעי ליה כדתניא ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. ha mibae leh k'detanya venirtza
lo lekhaper alav.
We have it in a ברייתא braitah that the same, same פסוק
pasuk is being addressed, should be accepted for him to atone for
him, like a duplication. רבי שמעון אומר את שעליו חייב באחריותו ואת
שאינו עליו אינו חייב באחריותו. rabbi shimon omer et she'alav hayav beachrayuto
ve'et she'eino alav eino hayav beachrayuto. So this is part of what
the discussion we just had: if somebody has responsibility, then this is
עליו alav and this is something that he has to bring,
even if he, something happens, we have those discussions somewhere else too
if something happens
to.
But if he doesn't have that kind of responsibility, if the animal
dies or it's lost, then it's not on him. ואמר רב יצחק
בר אבדימי Ve'amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi מאי טעמא mai ta'ama כיוון
דאמר עלי keivan de'amar alai כמאן דטעין ליה אכתפיה דמי. keman detayin
lei akatfei dami. Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi says what is what is
the reasoning, right, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
Once the person said עלי, alai, like this is I upon me
I will bring this offering, it's considered as if this offering is
like I don't know, it says loaded on his shoulders, but like
as if he's carrying it, right, he's carrying it with him, it's
a burden that he has and he can't get rid of that
burden until he unloads it, until he does the offering.
רב אשי Rav Ashi says from a different place: מונרצה לו לכפר
קאמר. mi-venirtza lo lekhaper ka'amar. That
the
הלכה halacha
that he can't somebody else cannot do the זריקה zerika for another
person, that the זריקה zerika is the main thing from can be
derived from a פסוק pasuk we saw earlier where it says מ-
ונרצה לו.
mi-
venirtza lo. It was like accepted for him. Again from this word
for him, because it could have just said ונרצה, venirtza, right, like
we say in פסח, Pesach, it was accepted, it's done. So
the
extra לו lo tells us that it remains with the owner. Okay,
so if we kept our thinking about what we have done so
far, and the גמרא Gemara does it for us because it knows
us, it says אשכחן זביחה וזריקה קבלה מנא לן? Ashkachan zvicha u'zerika,
kabbalah mina lan? So we talked about the owner about the זריקה
zerika and about the זביחה. zvicha. Where do we have proof for
קבלה kabbalah that this also must be done לשמה lishmah for the
sake of the intent of the
owner? וכי תימא ליליף מזביחה וזריקה מה לזביחה וזריקה שכן עבודה שחייבים
עליה בחוץ Ve-khi teima leilif mizvicha u'zerika? Mah le-zvicha u'zerika, sheken avodah
she-chayavim alei b'choutz? So back to the same exercise we tried to
do just a few minutes ago on the other עמוד. amud. Can
we learn it from the slaughter and the sprinkling? Just like we
said that this is something that must be done לשמה, lishmah, can
we just say that the same is for קבלה? kabbalah? And we
say, wait, there is something that is unique about זביחה zvicha and
זריקה zerika
that they are unique that
if
it's done outside the temple, there is a punishment of כרת karet
to do in it, as opposed to the קבלה kabbalah that is
not.
Is it כרת karet or מיתה בידי שמים? mitah bidei shamayim? Not
that you want either one.
I don't know.
Anyone know? Huh?
Yeah, from what I've studied,
just preparing for it, it's כרת.
karet. It says here it's from ויקרא Vayikra 17.
But there's another spot earlier there was another about מיתה בידי שמים,
mitah bidei shamayim, so I'm not I don't
remember what that sorry is, isn't that a category...
but
is מיתה בידי שמים mitah bidei shamayim like physical death that happens
like whatever lightning and כרת karet is more spiritual
and what does that mean? I don't
know.
אלא, Ela,
אמר
רב אשי,
amar Rav
Ashi, אתיא מאיל נזיר. atya mei-eil Nazir. We're going to a different
book, we're going to learn it from something else.
We're going to learn it from the ram of the
נזיר, Nazir, דכתיב de-khtiv says in פרשת נשא, parshat Nasso, ואת האיל
יעשה זבח שלמים, ve-et ha-ayil ya'aseh zevach shelamim, שתהא עשייתו לשם שלמים.
she-tehei asiyato leshem shelamim. When the נזיר Nazir completes his days of
נזירות, nezirot, how do we translate?
Nazirite? Okay. How do we translate נזיר? Nazir? Nazirite. And his days
of נזירות, nezirot, the days of his
Nazirite-ing, Nazirite-ship? Yeah, right. Then he brings the offering. שתהא עשייתו לשם
שלמים. she-tehei asiyato leshem shelamim. The offering should be for the sake
of שלמים. shelamim. ואינו ענין לשינוי קודש דנפקא ליה מהתם תנהו ענין
לשינוי בעלים. Ve-ino inyan l'shinui kodesh denafka lei mehatam, tenahu inyan l'shinui
be'alim. And if this is not necessary because we already proved all
the other things for the matter of change of the type of
the offering, right, of the שינוי קודש, shinui kodesh, then let's learn
from here the matters of change of owner. the owner of. אמר
ליה רב אחא בר אבא לרבא amar lei rav acha bar abba
le'rava
רגע rega in case this is what he said, Rav Acha bar
Abba לרבא le'rava he said רגע rega if this was not enough
complicated until now let me introduce a little twist to the story.
Okay. This is the whole
דף. daf.
אימא eima יעשה ya'aseh כלל klal זבח zevach
פרט prat כלל
ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט klal u'prat ein bi'khlal ela mah
she'ba'prat זביחה zvicha אין in מידי אחרינא לא midei achrina lo
פשיטא. pshita.
Okay.
כלל ופרט klal u'prat
right? This is the זבח zevach זביחה zvicha I think.
Every morning I think if I just had two more days to
draw this out. Okay.
זבח zevach is the פרט prat and the יעשה ya'aseh what it
said ואת האיל יעשה זבח ve'et ha'ayil ya'aseh zevach that supposedly is
the כלל klal
right? So this could be for other things and the זבח zevach
is the specific things.
So the זבח zevach is a detail right and according to this
principle of כלל ופרט klal u'prat the generalization and the detail, the
yes whatever the thing
then it includes only this specific thing and so from there we
learn that the זבח zevach is yes must be performed for the
owner but not all the other things and מידי אחרינא midei achrina
לא lo all the other things
the other things don't have to be performed for the sake of
the owner. Okay. אי כתיב יעשה שלמים זבח
ei ketiv
ya'aseh shlamim zevach maybe if they just changed the order of the
words right? The פסוק pasuk the פסוק pasuk said יעשה זבח שלמים
ya'aseh zevach shlamim but if it said יעשה שלמים זבח ya'aseh shlamim
zevach then if it was written this
way
then then whatever it would help us understand it in a different
way the שלמים shlamim will become a זבח zevach
and then yeah okay and then wait a
second
okay. If it said יעשה שלמים זבח ya'aseh shlamim zevach then the
זבח zevach would be the detail if I understand it correctly again
and the שלמים shlamim would be the כלל klal but now that
it's written backwards בדיוק bidyuk now that it's written
backwards after the איל ayil for a sacrifice of שלמים shlamim the
right then the term is incomplete.
It's okay let me read the whole thing in the גמרא. gemara.
אי כתיב יעשה שלמים זבח ei ketiv ya'aseh shlamim zevach if it
would be written differently כדאמרת k'de'amrat השתא כתיב יעשה זבח שלמים hashta
ketiv ya'aseh zevach shlamim הוי ליה hava lei כלל שאינו מלא klal
she'eino malei the generalization is incomplete
וכל כלל שאינו מלא אין דנים אותו בכלל ופרט. ve'chol klal she'eino
malei ein danim oto bi'khlal u'prat.
מה mah פשיטא לגמרי pshita legamre okay let's read it slowly.
Can we read it with huh? It's so circular. Yeah.
Yes. Okay.
It's almost like they think of what they want it to be
and they're really trying to figure out how to justify it.
We see where they're yeah we're out of how do
we
make sense no here but
I think if
you want to
okay go
say I mean you want me to this goes on for a
while. This is the specific term זבח zevach interrupts the general clause
שלמי שלמים.
shalmei shlamim.
Wow rabbi's in a if it's written before the תורה Torah states
what the general action is for that is
שלמים shlamim that clause can therefore not be considered a generalisation. That's
רש״י. Rashi. Hold on there's not even a good stopping point. Okay
so just apologies and tomorrow pick up from the issue of כלל
ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal and how do we eventually come to
learn that everything everything needs to be לשמה lishma on both sides.
So what I would have I would have just done a קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer.